Software Engineering Radio episode 108,
Simon Peyton Jones on functional
programming.
This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SE-Radio.net.
SE Radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days. Thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the podcast.
Welcome listeners to another episode of
Software Engineering Radio. This is
another episode on languages. We're
recording this at QCon and thanks to
Microsoft once again for giving us this
room here. This time we are talking to
Simon Peyton Jones.
He is uh
a believer in Haskell as I learned this
morning in his talk. So, we're going to
talk about functional programming,
Haskell, and
related topics. So, Simon, welcome to
the show. Thank you very much. So, why
don't you introduce yourself to our
listeners, personal background, where do
you work, what do you do?
I work at Microsoft Research Lab in
Cambridge. I've been there for about 10
years now. I work in the programming
languages group. Before that, I was a
professor at the University of Glasgow.
I was there for 10 years and before
that, I was a lecturer at University
College London
for 7 years and before that, I spent 2
years in industry and that that
that made me realize how hard all you
guys work.
So, I thought I would
get a job in a university instead.
Yeah.
Um so, now now my now my job's
programming languages research and um
uh so, I get to study more or less what
I like and publish very freely.
Mhm.
Um so, that's a very exciting job to
have, but it's not
uh we get access to Microsoft's
Microsoft developers. I talk to them
quite a bit, but also I can work on
things that are not directly related to
Microsoft's products at all.
Yeah. One example for that is Haskell
because I think it's not a Microsoft
product, or is it?
No, Haskell is not a Microsoft product.
Okay.
Um alas.
Uh it's uh so I've been um interested in
functional programming ever since I was
an undergraduate. In fact, when I first
did a a short course on functional
programming, I became addicted to the
the uh the incredible elegance of
writing uh tiny functions that did
awesome things.
Yeah.
Uh so ever since then, my my research
has really been focused around turning
functional programming into something
that moves from it being an uh clever
idea into something that you could use
in a real world.
Right.
And as a vehicle for that, I was
involved in the design and development
of this language called Haskell.
Mhm.
Because quite a few this this was the uh
the late 1980s. Quite a few of us of us
were um
working in different research labs on
non-strict or lazy functional
programming languages, but we all had a
different one.
Mhm.
So then we all got together at a
conference and said, "We should have one
language." So then we then we we met and
over several years we developed this
language called Haskell that um that is
now like 15 or 17 years old.
Okay.
But it's quite a mature language.
Yeah.
Um
and it's developed quite a bit over that
time as well.
So so one of the hallmarks of of Has
Haskell as as far as I understand it is
that it's one of the few really pure
functional languages. So why don't you
explain what functional languages are in
general and and especially what makes
them pure and why this is important.
A good way to start is to think about a
spreadsheet. When you write a
spreadsheet, you write formulas that uh
compute the value of a cell from the
values of other cells.
And
in a formula, you wouldn't write in cell
A2, you wouldn't write equals um print
something followed by three
uh because you wouldn't know when that
would be executed. It'd be an odd thing
to do. So the formula in your cells
simply compute values from other values.
It doesn't make sense for them to do
anything else.
And in the context of a spreadsheet, we
don't question that.
So that's what I mean by purity in which
uh
functions compute values from their
inputs and they can be a computer result
value.
Something you used this morning was to
contrast the imperative style which is
location-oriented, location-based with
the value-based approach in functions.
Right. Right. So, in an imperative
program, the way the way an imperative
program works is the program counter
moves down one statement at a time. And
as it moves down, the the values of
mutable locations change. So, a location
called X is not the X is not the name of
a value. X is the name of a location
whose value changes over time.
Whereas in a functional language, if you
have a variable called X, it's the name
for a value. Anywhere that X is in
scope, it has the same value.
Mhm.
Yeah. And that's a quite a big shift in
programming paradigm.
Mhm.
Indeed. hear about this, if you've never
done any functional programming before,
my first question was when I was
thinking about this as an undergraduate,
is can you write any useful programs
at all?
in such an emasculated language, right?
One that you does not even have an
assignment statement. An assignment
statement is the very fabric out of
which we build the programs that we're
all used to. And the amazing thing is,
yes, you can.
Although handling state and side effect
is a is an interesting topic there which
we'll discuss later, I guess.
That's right. Yes.
Yeah. What I hear often in in the
context of functional languages is is
the lambda calculus. Can you maybe say a
couple of words about that?
So, I suppose the lambda calculus is the
functional programming as um I don't
know, the X86 or Z80 is to um imperative
programming. So, the lambda calculus is
kind of like the most boiled down
version of functional programming you
can imagine.
Mhm.
So, the lambda calculus is a is a tiny
language with only three constructs,
variables,
lambda abstractions, and application.
So, it's got it's just got three
syntactic forms and one reduction rule.
And yet, you can translate monstrously
complicated Haskell programs into this
tiny calculus.
So, and then you can see you can watch
the tiny calculus executing. So, you
could almost think of the lambda
calculus as being like the execution
mechanism for a functional program. It
doesn't actually happen like that, but
it's not a bad way to think of it. So,
the lambda calculus is the essence of
functional programming in an incredibly
small space.
You already said that there is this
idea of applying something, applying a
function of values resulting in new
value, which you can then use. So, so
having values as part of functions
probably clear to everybody who has seen
functions in math. But in functional
programming, functions are also values.
Right, right. So,
the question is what kind of arguments
can a function take?
Right.
So, we're used to functions taking
arguments that are integers or floats or
perhaps lists or trees.
We're not quite so used to them taking
arguments that are functions.
But after you start to after you start
to think about it, if you have a
um
uh you may find yourself writing the
same pattern again and again. So,
supposing you find yourself writing a a
function that um doubles every element
of a list. And then later you find
yourself writing a function that
troubles every element of a list or
reverses every element of a list. Well,
then you think maybe I could just write
one function that just that that that
does something to every element of the
list. And what's the something? Oh, I'll
pass that as an argument. What does that
mean? I'm passing a function as an
argument. Another even easier example,
filtering a list.
Right.
So, if you want to take a list and you
want to say, "Give me all the even
elements." then what do you want to give
to filter? You want to give it a a
predicate function, that is a function
from list element to bool.
Right.
All right. And and it applies that
function. So, it's very natural to want
to pass functions as data. And that's
something that that's called
higher-order functional programming. And
it's and it's that's something that any
functional language allows you to do.
Mhm.
So, it's also it's also possible to do
this in in conventional mainstream
object-oriented programming languages
these days. They're usually called
delegates.
Right. Yeah.
And delegate is just a kind of function
that you can pass as an argument.
Yeah. One thing that that became really
crystal clear in in the slides you've
shown this morning is that because
functions are the essential building
blocks of a functional language, um they
require very very very little syntactic
overhead. So, um it really reads very
elegantly. And and for example, currying
um doesn't require any special thing.
You just call a function with only one
argument and that implicitly returns
assuming it had several before that the
carried function. So, this is is really
nice.
Right. There's there's quite a
quite an economy of concept there. That
a function of
the way you mentioned currying, which
some of your listeners may may not know
about. So, but the idea in its essence
is is pretty simple. It says
a function of two arguments, you can
think of it this way. It's a function
that takes one argument
and returns a function
of one argument, which returns the final
result. So, take the addition function.
The addition function if applied to an
argument three, a single argument three,
returns a function. And what does that
function do? It adds three to things.
Mhm. Yep.
So, there we've as it were boiled down
instead of having multi-argument
functions, we can now have
single-argument functions. And in fact,
in Haskell, it's true to say that every
function only takes one argument.
Mhm.
Um but it can consume but it can return
a function which takes another. And it
turns out that by
that you can actually pass several.
Oh, yes, of course. So, so when we write
F space A, we mean F applied to A. When
we write F space A space B, we mean F
applied to A
applied to B. So, function application
in Haskell is left associative.
Is this also how it's implemented
literally? Or is this just a meta
metaphor to think about it? Or is
It's how you think about it. It's not
No, so in the actual implementation um
inside our compiler for Haskell, no, we
do some analysis to say this function
actually can't do any work until it's
given three arguments."
Okay.
So, we'll code it as a we'll implement
it as a as a piece of you know, machine
code that demands three arguments. If
it's given fewer, we'll save them up
somewhere.
Okay.
And arrange to give it to them later.
Mhm. So, if we talk about the philosophy
of Haskell being a pure language, then I
guess one of the really well, obviously
uh important building blocks is the side
effect freeness of of it. So,
That's what purity means, yes.
Exactly.
So, so um can you elaborate a little bit
about what side effects are, and
especially why they might be a problem?
Uh so, what's a side effect? So, a side
effect is when you're when you you call
a procedure and it does something other
than transform its arguments into a new
result value. So, there's something
other that it might do. It might uh
write into mutable state, persistent
mutable state. It might uh
do some input. It might take some input
from read to disk. It might delete
files. It might launch missiles. It
might
Uh
so, a side effect is anything is in fact
anything other than
returning a result.
Yeah.
That's computed from the inputs. Now,
why are these bad? Because after all,
that's what imperative programs do all
the time. In fact, you see many many
procedures that who which have a void
result type. You see void F of ABC.
Yeah.
And so, the only reason you call it,
right, is to have the side effect,
right? But you don't you you're not
interested in the result. It's void
after all. You know what it's going to
be.
So, why are side effects bad? Well,
um
let me instead say, "Why is purity
good?" So, at the moment, side effects
are so much part of the fabric of our
present languages that it's hard to see
how you could do without them. But let's
imagine that you could work in a pure
language. Then what would you get? So,
uh the one thing that's very helpful is
programs can become easier to understand
and reason about because there's less
happening behind the scenes.
Mhm.
It can also be easier to maintain. So,
when I make a change to a function, that
usually changes its interface, right?
So, when I change its interface, I
change its type, and now the compiler
tells me there are lots of other places
I need to change. If instead of changing
the interface of a function, if it still
has type int to void, but instead it,
you know, modifies one more or fewer
global variables, then it's harder to
see what consequent effects there might
be. So, maintenance then tends to be a
bit different. Testing is different,
too.
If you want to test a side-effecting
function, then what do you have to do?
You have to set up the state of the
world to be ready to call it, call it,
inspect the state of the world and see
if the expected state change has taken
place. So, and by the way, you might
have had to copy bits of the initial
state of the world first.
So, that you can compare them before and
after.
That's where mock objects come in,
right? Where you can replace parts of
the real world with simulated parts to
to achieve exactly this goal.
Right, right. And it's not that it can't
be done, but that it's a bit of an
uphill struggle. And then if we could do
without it, this would be good. And we
can do it in a
in a pure world, if you could work in a
pure world.
Uh this would be very nice, but what do
you do? Well, um
you can test a function simply by giving
it a test some test values as its input
and looking at its output.
Right.
So, if you're testing the sine function,
you give it, you know, 0.1 and you look
at the output, and you look at give it
0.2 and you look at its output. There's
no state to set up, there's no state to
There's no old and there's no new.
Right.
Um if you're testing a set uh the set
union function, you don't need to worry
that set union will modify the the input
set. Just compare the input set with the
output set. So, testing is particularly
easy, and in fact, that is that leads
directly to better automation. So,
there's some rather nice testing tools
available for Haskell. One of which is
developed by some colleagues of mine,
it's called QuickCheck, and it has a
rather beautiful property that you just
tell me the type of a function, you tell
QuickCheck the type of a function, and
it'll generate random data suitable for
functions of that type, and give you
some um test some of its properties.
It's rather remarkable, and it's because
all the interfaces are on the surface.
Another reason you might be interested
in purity is that it gives you a a
better handle on parallelism. It doesn't
make parallelism easy,
Yeah.
but it kind of makes it, you know, feel
a bit more within reach. In a imperative
programming with
mutant side effects on global variables,
it's hard to put your hand on your heart
and say you're sure that this thing is
thread safe.
Right.
Use locks and condition variables and
you you hope and pray and you establish
rules and invariants and
it's very difficult to get right.
Right.
Uh
in a purely functional world, it's
actually very difficult to get wrong.
Right? Because because your program is
kind of inherently you don't have any
locks and condition variables because
there's no mutable state to lock.
That said,
it's not true to say that you can just
press a button on a functional program
and it and it'll run in parallel because
uh for a number of reasons, one is that
the data dependencies within the program
might sequentialize it.
Right.
And yeah. Uh and so if you think about
its data flow diagram, it just might not
be parallelized at all.
Mhm.
Less obviously, even if it is quite
parallel, it may be difficult to get a
sufficiently large level of granularity
um
to execute efficiently. So, I don't
think it's parallelism without tears,
but it kind of gives you a chance in a
way that the imperative by default with
shared mutable state makes things very
difficult.
Mhm.
Since you don't have mutable state,
recursion is something that's used quite
a bit.
Right.
So, recursion effectively replaces
iteration.
Right.
Because iteration relies on going around
the same code with the same locations
with different values and in the
so if you don't have mutable values,
that kind of iteration doesn't work. So,
yes, recursion replaces it.
And and um there are a couple of
optimizations to make uh opti- recursion
feasible performance-wise. Um
I think you mentioned two this morning
in your talk. Obviously, one is tail
recursion
Yeah.
and the other one is uh lazy evaluation
uh or memoization, I think you called
it. So, why don't you elaborate on
Well, so tail recursion is is the one
that you must do to um
uh if you're to reasonably claim to be
able to execute arbitrary programs in
the with the same kind of asymptotic
efficiency as you can with an imperative
program. So, all tail recursion means is
if a function calls itself or indeed any
other function, and that's the last
thing it does, so sort of
um
f of x is uh, you know, if something
then f of x prime,
else something else. So, so the last
thing it does is to call itself, then
instead of instead of uh,
calling itself or the other function and
then when you come back from that
removing the current stack frame, you
remove the current stack frame right
away. So, it's an implementation thing,
but it's important because it means that
when you do something that amounts to a
loop,
Yeah.
just do something a thousand times, you
don't grow stack that's a thousand deep.
Right. Now, so in practice that that
turns out to be very important.
Mhm.
Uh, and any Haskell implementation will
do that. Okay.
Uh,
it's a little tricky if you're compiling
to um, to dot net or to
JVM.
if that's the target of the of the
functional language implementation, then
you have a tougher time because those
language platforms don't support tail
recursion very well. They do somewhat.
Yeah.
Actually, dot net does reasonably well,
partly because there were some
functional programming types um,
involved when dot net was being
designed.
Mhm.
Uh, however, what your other your other
point was lazy evaluation. So, lazy
evaluation I think is not is not
fundamental to purity.
Mhm.
Uh, you could have a So, lazy evaluation
means that when you call a function,
you don't evaluate its arguments before
the call. Instead, you pass to the
function a kind of suspension or thunk
or recipe.
Closure?
A closure, yes.
Yeah, just to get the term
Yes, or closure, so there's multiple
names all for the same idea. You wrap up
the the argument. You don't compute it
in advance. You wrap it up and then if
the function inside itself ever needs
the value of that argument, it pokes on
the thunk or closure or suspension and
that causes it to then do the
computation computation is delayed.
That's that's called laziness or call by
call by need or call by name.
As distinct from call by value
which is the the normal way that that
Lisp or indeed C# would work.
And of course that's important for an if
statement for example because you want
to evaluate only the then or the else
part. So that's where it comes in.
Yes, that's a good point. So if you want
to implement if not as the language
construct but as a function
just just another function. Yes. Well,
so in Lisp there's cond you see which is
a language construct pretty much. Or
maybe it's a macro or something. But
it's something it's not just an ordinary
function because an ordinary function in
Lisp would evaluate its arguments. Yes.
So in a lazy language you really can
implement if as a just as a function.
Yeah, I think and then you had this this
morning that you showed how to
implement various control structures for
forever.
That's a little bit different to lazy
evaluation. That's more to do with this
monadic side effecting stuff.
Which which we'll get to but
So laziness is
laziness is a distinctive feature of
Haskell, right? There's not very many
lazy functional programming languages.
So it's one of Haskell's distinctive
features and actually it's it's the
reason that Haskell has stayed pure
because a
if you're going to have a lazy language
that means that a function
may evaluate its argument at some time
that perhaps is a bit harder for the
hard for the caller of the function to
know. That's really the to do with the
implementation of the function, right?
When it evaluates its argument. So if
its argument was to have side effects
then it'd be hard for the caller to know
whether the side effects would take
place at all and if so in what order
relative to everything else.
So what that means is that it's it's
much more there's a it's much less
reasonable to just say, "Oh, we'll allow
you to do side effects after all inside
these quotes functions then it is in a
call by value language. So in effect
Haskell's laziness which I think is a
super property. I really love
programming in lazy language but in the
end when push comes to shove the
important thing is purity.
Right.
And laziness is a kind of
helped us to stay pure but and it's
wonderful in itself.
Mhm.
But it's not it's not the it's not mine
that's the high order bit is be pure.
Yeah. So the other thing you mentioned
this morning was this memorization thing
that a function that's called several
times as a part of a recursion tree
right only is executed once and the
return value is cached to optimize
performance.
Yeah no I shouldn't shouldn't I hope I
didn't mislead you into thinking that
will happen automatically.
It's not the case the implementation
behind the scenes is going around
looking for every call and saying oh I
bet have I called that function with the
same value before.
I was actually misled and you know why?
Because I'm I'm involved with a
a tool for model driven software
development and we have a somewhat
functional language in there and it has
exactly that feature. If during one
basically execution of a script you call
the same function several times it's
actually only ever evaluated once. It's
very useful for graph transformation.
Yes.
So and I kind of related that to this
memorization you mentioned this morning.
a perfectly sound implementation.
But it's quite an expensive one to apply
to every function all the time.
Yes.
Because it means you have to retain all
old function calls and their results
forever.
Yes and that's not what we do. It's only
for create functions functions that
actually create new objects
because oh well I don't want to get into
this.
Yeah.
It's useful in practice for graph
transformation.
So I can imagine it's in particular
circumstances and it would be and it
would be nice to be able to point to
some function say memoize this one.
Exactly.
interact with laziness too. If you
haven't evaluated the argument yet you
might be applying it to two you might be
really saying f of two but it's f of
something which evaluates to two. But
you haven't evaluated it yet.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
So anyway the the point is that you
might want to do at you might want to do
a static transformation that is a
transformation at compile time that
transforms an inefficient program into
an efficient one by gaining extra
sharing. This is really what dynamic
programming is about and that that
transformation is justified by the side
effect free nature of the calls.
Right, because you can yeah, it's safe
to do these things.
That's right. So so we we said or you
said that um the the core abstractions
in functional programming languages are
obviously functions. So what what's the
role of data types? Do you have classes?
I mean how how does that how does that
go together? I mean
Oh oh data data types are terribly
important. So we define date new data
types all the time.
Okay.
Uh so they're they're typically um
uh what's called algebraic data types.
So you say uh the way you do it is you
say here's a new data type. I'll call it
uh I'll call it T and it has
constructors A, B, and C and A has three
fields, an int, a float, and a bool and
B has no fields and C has one field
that's an int.
Yep.
So you'd write So data type T is A of
int, float, bool or B or C of float.
Mhm.
Something like that.
Yep.
Now those A, B, and C are called the
constructors. So it's pretty similar to
an object-oriented language with an
abstract class T and three um sub
classes, final sub classes A, B, and C.
Yeah.
So then you can build uh values of type
T by using A, B, and C as constructors.
You can say A of three, true, 4.0 or
just B or C of 3.0. Those would each
build a value of type T. But you can
also use them in pattern matching.
Right? So then you say F applied to open
brackets
A of X, Y, Z equals and so that says F
applied to that kind of pattern
does this answer, F applied to B does
this, F applied to C of something does
that. So you define functions by cases.
Right, so just to connect to a previous
episode, we had uh in Erlang we also
discussed these things. Erlang has these
too and also in Scala.
Yes. Yes. Yes. So in Erlang the you
don't declare a new data type. You can
just do this pattern matching thing uh
across you know any any in a in a more
free-wheeling way.
Yeah. So, that has advantages because it
means that you can um
uh sometimes untyped programming is is
very is in is very convenient, but if
you're writing uh if you're writing a
function and you say it's quite nice to
be able to say, in fact, it's really
helpful from a software engineering
point of view to say
this F takes a value of type T. T has
exactly three cases, A, B, and C. Done.
Mhm.
Right? I have covered all the cases. I
know that at runtime I'm never going to
get a value that I don't recognize here.
Yeah.
That's a very powerful static guarantee
that you can get out of this kind of
thing. So, data types very important,
but they don't have the same usually uh
it's not impossible to do this. Scala
Scala does um
Scala lifts some of these restrictions,
but in most functional languages when
you declare a data type you can't then
add new constructors to it later.
Yeah.
And sometimes that's very inconvenient
not being able to add later, and most of
the time it's just fine.
Yeah.
Um so, data types very important.
Functions and data types play very
nicely together.
Yeah. Just in a in a somewhat different
way than you might expect from
traditional programming.
Yes. Yes. So, a data type is rather a
passive thing, right? So, in a in an
object-oriented language when you
declare a new class, you usually give it
behavior.
Right.
Right? So, in a functional language when
you declare a new data type uh oh, wait
a moment. When you when you're saying to
give it new you give it some behavior,
then you that makes it easy to add new
types with the same operations, but
adding a new operation, of course, is a
bit more difficult. This is the standard
uh sort of trade-off that that lots of
people have discussed, but um I'm sure
most of your listeners will be familiar
with this, but functional languages tend
to the the shoe is on the other foot.
It's inconvenient in a different way.
Like, you have a data type. It's easy to
add new functions over that type, but
it's not so easy to add a new uh new uh
variants of the data type.
Yeah. Yeah.
Um and uh people have tried quite hard
to build languages that support both. Um
and uh and that that's a it's a very
worthy endeavor, but not not something
that's I don't know. I
We nobody's found anything that's that's
completely satisfying yet. I think Scala
is probably one of the best
instantiations of such an attempt.
Yeah. Okay, so let's talk about side
effects.
Ah, all right.
Or maybe not talk about them because we
don't want them or maybe
But we want them sometimes, don't
Right. That's exactly the point because
writing a piece of software that has no
side effects, as you said this morning,
will heat up the CPU and don't do
anything else.
So, we clearly have to deal with side
effects somehow.
Yeah.
So, um why don't you
you know, give us an overview of how you
resolve those ten this tension between
not really wanting side effects, but
still somehow still having them and
maybe managing or containing them?
Right. For a for a long time in Haskell
it was a bit we we were very pure and
also rather embarrassed because we had a
purely functional language which
couldn't do very much because it had
these very well, essentially no side
effects. So, the whole program was a
function from type string to string. But
um that that led us to uh eventually to
develop this idea which is called
monads.
So, that was originally This is a part
of I mean, it was invented by the
Haskell Haskell group. Oh, I didn't know
that. Okay.
That it was uh Phil Wadler at Glasgow
while where I was a professor in
I see.
in the early '90s and and so Phil has a
brain the size of a small asteroid and
he
he was he was good at maths and category
theory, too. And he spotted these these
uh very clever, but deeply obscure
papers by Eugenio Moggi, who's an
Italian with very small glasses, smaller
than yours. Like this little small round
glasses. Brilliant guy. Um and Phil
understood Eugenio's papers and said,
"Oh, I could write a program that does
this." And then I looked at Phil's work
and said, "We could use this to do
imperative functional programming, to do
side effects inside a Haskell program
without polluting the whole language
with side effects everywhere." So, we
wrote this paper called imperative
functional programming, which
turned out to be sort of be the start of
a really interesting development of
figuring out how to mix side effects
into a purely functional setting without
throwing the baby out with the
bathwater.
Mhm.
Um so the way
briefly that it's done is to is is
the two the side effect bits and the
pure bits are kept apart by the type
system.
Okay.
So
uh a function with type um
uh what in the talk that I talked this
morning I gave the example of a function
called to upper which has that string to
string.
Right.
And it converts a string to uppercase.
It's type is string arrow string.
Mhm.
So you know that it doesn't do any input
output. It can't do anything else. It
takes a string, it delivers a string,
that's all.
But if you see another function get user
input
whose type is string arrow IO of string
Mhm.
So you think of this in the same way as
you think would might think of string
arrow list of string or string arrow
array of string. The IO of is a type
constructor of some kind. They're like a
like in generics, right?
Mhm.
So string to IO of string. Now that IO
thing says
here some input output might happen.
So it says
get user input says give me a string and
I will give you back an IO computation.
And an IO computation is something that
can do some input output and then return
a value of a of the given type, the
string in this case.
And because it's a part of the type
system, the compiler can know about it
and not apply all those reordering and
other optimizations because that would
be dangerous here.
That's right. That's exactly right.
You know what this reminded me of when I
was thinking about the stuff this
morning? It's a little bit like the
volatile keyword in C, which basically
says don't touch this, don't optimize
this because this variable to which the
volatile is is is attached is modified
from behind your back from the operating
system or somewhere. Of course it's the
other way around. It's not the program
outputs, it's something changes the
program. But it's basically a hint at
the compiler, you know, don't mess with
that. Is that fair to say in some way?
Yes, that's true, but it's much less
draconian than that.
Okay.
So, if I have a function of type string
arrow IO of string, for example, and
it's perfectly okay for me to inline
that function.
Right.
is still a pure object. So, I can inline
it. I can move the function around. And
so, and what else can I do? I can um
uh I can store an a value of type IOT in
a data structure or pass it as an
argument to a function or return it as a
result. It's very first-class value.
Yeah.
So, in fact, the compiler So, I would
imagine I've never I've not seen the
implementation of volatile and so forth.
I. I've just
But, I'm guessing that there's a lot of
ad hoc jiggery-pokery to say to switch
off things when there's a volatile
kicking around anyway.
Mhm.
Um but, with this with this monad stuff,
it's much simpler than that.
So, what happens in inside our compiler
is that we the as far as the compiler is
concerned, something of type IOT looks
very like a function from world to a
pair of A and world.
Right.
So, one of these computations is
represented as well as a function.
So, it's rather Haskell-centric view of
the the universe to
that the that an IO computation takes in
the entire universe
Right.
and transforms the universe a little bit
by mutating one variable in it and
returns a new slightly modified
universe. But, as far as the compiler
concerned, that's fine. What that means
is that the
all this IO stuff is simply transformed
as far as the compiler is concerned into
more lambdas. And once that's done, it
optimizes those lambdas
All right.
like crazy, just like any other lambda.
Okay.
So, in fact, it's it's a very if you
like, it's a very principled way of
switching off optimizations
that means that 90% of the compiler
doesn't even need to know there's any
funny business going on at all.
Another thing you you said this morning
is that it's a way or that monads are a
way of classifying side effects. So, do
you have only the IO monad or are there
other monads in in or monadic types of
what what monadic type constructors in
in in Haskell?
Oh, lots. Lots. So, from a very early
stage we realized that
um we didn't just have the idea of the
IO monad as something by itself. We had
the idea of um of a it's it's almost a
design pattern, a monadic design
Mhm.
of which IO is one instance.
Right. Yeah.
Um and a state transformer is another
instance and exception monad is another
instance. And in fact, it's not even
it's not built into the language or its
libraries how many instances there
should be.
So, this is actually directly supported
in the language design by a mechanism
called type classes, which is used for
all sorts of other purposes, too. Mhm.
Type classes are a way of uh describing
a a computation pattern a design
pattern, if you like.
Yeah.
And um
and so the the monad class in Haskell,
so you shouldn't think object-oriented
class. You should
No, the class of types.
It's more like yeah, it's more like a
design design pattern and the monad
design pattern in Haskell.
Okay.
Um
then allows any anybody, you, to uh in
your next Haskell program you write, you
can build a new monad that that's
supported syntactically by the compiler
with do notation and so forth.
Mhm.
And in which all the monad combinators,
like that forever thing that I showed
you, and the four thing that I showed
you this morning, those will work on
your new monad just as they did on all
the old ones.
That's the relationship to control
structures.
Yes. Yes, that's right. So, what that
means is that it's that actually what we
discovered is not a particular
uh monad IO, but rather a design pattern
and we found a way to fit that design
pattern into Haskell's existing type
class mechanism in a in in what was I
don't think we should take credit for
this part. It turned out to be a very
beautiful way. Just fitted nicely.
Yeah. So, another interesting thing you
mentioned this morning um was the
relationship to transactional memory. We
had an episode on transactional memory
with I forget who what the name of the
author was. There was a paper at last
year's OOPSLA about the analogy between
garbage collection and transactional
memory.
Oh, yes.
So, that was actually
Dan Grossman.
Exactly. Right. Yeah.
Yes, so he would have had a nice OOPSLA
essay about this.
So, we had we had an interview with him.
And uh so so can you let us know that
the relationship between monadic stuff
and the atomic
keyword and transactional memory?
here's a here's a beautiful example of
wishing to classify effects more finely
than just, you know, having IO or pure.
Right? Because what we really want to
say is uh so let's just revise
transactional memory. What you want to
be able to say is atomically do this and
this and this and this, where these
things are mutations of transactional
variables.
Mhm.
You are not allowed to say atomically do
this and this and launch the missiles
and do that and that.
Mhm.
Why not? Because the transaction is
supposed to execute um
uh it's supposed to be able to it's
supposed to be possible to execute it
optimistically and then roll back and
try again, right? So, it's important
that it doesn't make any commitments
like, you know, destroying small
countries um
before it knows that it's ready to
commit.
Yeah.
So, it's very helpful to be able to
classify the side effects not to say it
has no side effects at all, but to say
this block of code, this
uh expression, does only side effects on
transacted variables.
So,
in STM Haskell,
the atomic construct, it's not a
language construct, it's just a
function. Yeah. And its type is STM A
arrow IO A.
Mhm.
Which means it takes as its argument a
computation A A that does STM-like
things, so a side-effecting computation,
but one that can only manipulate
transacted variables, and it runs it
atomically, and delivers the result into
the IO monad, which is this this richer
monad. So, there's kind of
stratification of effects that the STM
monad kind of limited effects and it can
deliver its result to the IO monad,
which has lots of effects. And inside
the STM monad, you may be calling pure
functions that have no effect at all.
Yeah. Another thing to conclude this
side effect side effect discussion, I
guess, is that um
Of course, if you if you have a function
whose return type is not IO, so it's
just maybe string
Uh-huh.
and you call a function inside that
function whose return type is IO string
or something, then you will probably get
a compile error or something. So,
because the compiler can check from the
type system how the
pollution, the non-pureness propagates
through the program.
Yeah, that's right.
It's a bit like a throw statement.
It would be like adding three to true.
Right.
The compiler just says type error.
Yeah.
So, if you call an IO-ish function
inside a allegedly pure one
Yeah.
type error.
Yes. So, that does mean you get pretty
robust guarantees
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
about where where impurity is happening.
Mhm.
Okay, so let's talk a little bit about
the benefits and liabilities of the
functional approach in general. What I
what I saw this morning, I mean, it
wasn't new to me this morning, but it it
was nicely illustrated also in Ted
Neward's F# talk. Um that um the
notation can become quite compact.
Uh what do you think uh does this mean
for writability and readability?
I mean
how likely I'm provoking of course. So,
how likely is it if if you write a
nicely compact function, I can
understand it?
It's often the case that people say I
rewrote my program in a functional style
and it became very much shorter.
That's that's a common observation.
Yeah.
It's not invariably the case. Sometimes
there are programs that just have lots
and lots of things that must be done,
you know,
ranks of of buttons that must be
arranged or and and there's no way to no
way to short it. But But but it often
does happen.
It's certainly possible to write obscure
functional programs.
Like like one-liners. I remember when I
first learned APL,
uh I was all excited because uh I
discovered that you could write uh you
could you could write an APL program on
three or four lines, but you could
sometimes write the same program on one
line.
Yeah. A very long line with huge
intermediate arrays, and it would still
work. I thought this was just the best
thing since sliced bread. But my um my
mentor at that stage, I was I was 18, uh
said,
"Doing that is like carving a piece of
wire out of marble.
It demonstrates your skill as a carver,
but it's really not what marble was
meant for as a medium, right?"
So, in the same way in in functional
programs, it's possible to get so
abstract and to to try to make things so
compact that it becomes quite difficult
to understand the program. But um
but I will say that
I you know, I so I don't want to defend
that style, but nevertheless, it has
does in practice seem to be a medium in
which it's possible to
build new abstractions that match your
particular application.
Mhm.
So, uh
um so then and then in effect you build
up a a vocabulary of functions that
match your application. So, now you can
It's almost like having a
domain-specific programming language.
I was about to mention that, yeah. So,
is there any experience specifically
about using Haskell for internal DSLs?
Oh. Oh, well, if you internal DSLs
Well, building DSLs inside
lots. If you type Haskell DSL into
Google, you'll get lots of hits.
So, one of the standard standard
examples is a parsers. Right? So, we're
familiar with Yacc and Lex, which let
you So, they take a different language,
that's Yacc's input language, and
transform it into C.
Yeah.
So, instead, uh to build a a Haskell um
parser, the um what you can do is you
can write a
uh
uh a library
with uh
whose which has a type like parser of A,
meaning So, parser of A is a parser
which delivers values of type A.
Mhm.
So, underneath the parser is probably a
consumes a string and produces a
depleted string and a value of type A.
Yeah.
But, just think of it as a parser
producing values of type A. Now, you can
imagine a a combinator, a function that
takes two parsers, a parser of A and a
parser of B,
and combines them together to make a
parser of AB pairs.
Mhm.
What does that do? Well, it parses the A
value, then it parses the B value.
And then you can imagine a combinator
that goes many, you know, written star
sometimes in in in
syntaxes. So, many of P means has many
has type parser of A to parser of list
of A. And what it does is it parses as
many copies of A as it can and then it
returns them as a list.
So, now what what what you find is that
So, now you might might want
if you want a parser for an alphabetic
identifier, you might find yourself
writing,
you know, alpha, you know, then So, then
is the the combining form. Alpha then
many of, you know, alpha or num.
Mhm.
Right. So, So, this many and then and or
are all parser combining things. So, in
effect, the this many and or things are
stuff that you would would form part of
the, as it were, the concrete syntax in
Yacc.
Yeah.
They're just infix functions in Haskell.
You can define your own infix functions.
So, it turns out that you can pretty
much write down something a grammar that
looks a bit like a Yacc grammar,
Yeah.
but it is a Haskell program.
Cool.
So, that's an embedded domain-specific
language, because instead of being a
domain-specific language written in its
own syntax, it's a domain-specific
language written in the syntax of the
host language. And that's very good if
you can you know, if you can make that
work, it's brilliant, because then you
get all the facilities of the host
language, modules and functions, to to
let you scale up.
And the ability to define your own new
control structures using the stuff we
discussed before is of course also
really good building block for defining
DSLs.
Yeah. And in fact, parsers, you'll be
unsurprised to hear, form a
and the same do notation and the same
combinators that work on IO computations
will work on parsers, too, rather
remarkably.
Okay. So, after discussing all these
concepts and theory, let's take a brief
look at
the practice. So, where is where and how
is Haskell used today?
Oh, so Haskell is being used by
a bewildering variety of people today.
So, Haskell has moved from, I would say
I would say for a long time Haskell was
used by hundreds or a small number of
thousands of users, and now it's sort of
sprouted by a factor of about 10, I
would say, in the last 5 years or
something. Something big has happened.
Is this because of the parallelism
thing?
I don't really know what suddenly made
this happen. It could be It could be
that functional programming is being
taught at universities for long enough.
Right. Okay.
There's, you know, even managers have
heard of
It could be that Haskell's been
Somehow it's There's something in the
air.
It may be that parallelism is helping
push things over the hill, but um And
what So, what's Haskell being used for?
Haskell's used by a lot of banks.
People build web applications using
Haskell. They build machine learning
kind of applications. They build gene
sequencing things. It's I mean, it's a
general-purpose programming language.
fair to say that it's especially
suitable for algorithm-heavy stuff as
opposed to, you know, like distributed
systems, web architecture, blah blah
stuff?
So, yes. So, if you've got a complicated
algorithm which with with which data
structures
Yeah.
then it's particularly good, right? If
you've got something where the principal
business is you've got to, you know,
you've got to take apart an immense gob
of XML, do something meaningless to it,
and send it out again,
do something modest to it, right? Then
it's really helpful to have really big
libraries that hack XML apart. That's
the other thing that's happened in the
last few years is that a lot more
libraries are available for Haskell. So,
few years ago there was nothing
equivalent to CPAN. Now we got an
equivalent to CPAN, it's called Hackage.
And every month 100 people upload new
libraries, 100 unique new libraries a
month go up there. Now, they're of
variable quality,
Sure.
But nevertheless, you know, from zero to
100 a month is a big change. It's a sea
change. What are the implementations
like? There's some several
different
or but all open-source implementations
of Haskell available.
or so or so.
Yes, so there's there's an interpreter
called Hugs. A
Our compiler is called GHC, the Glasgow
Haskell Compiler. Glasgow is where I was
at university.
Yeah.
Um it's probably the the most widely
used Haskell compiler just because it
compiles pretty good code.
Mhm.
Um and it has an interpreter that comes
with it as well. And it comes with
program coverage tools and profiling
tools. So it's a pretty Then there's
another
uh sort of laboratory kind of uh
compiler called NHC, which is very nice
because it's much more easy to modify.
It's a smaller, more manageable beast.
Whereas GHC is pretty big beast these
days.
Mhm.
Is there a relationship to F Sharp? I
overheard this morning that you're like
two doors away from Don Syme, who
Yes, so Don Don Syme's my my immediate
neighbor. He's part of the same group
and I'm I'm just three or four doors
down from him. Um so the relationship to
F Sharp is is mainly an intellectual
one. So Don Don for quite a while was
said said, "Simon, come on. You You got
Get your finger out and get Haskell onto
.NET."
And for various reasons, that's quite
difficult to do because
uh Haskell is a pure language and .NET
is not.
Right.
Right? And so that's a And Haskell needs
uh
there's various Haskell aspects of
Haskell's type system that don't that
are richer than .NET's. Like, if you're
prepared to adopt .NET's type system,
that's okay. But unfortunately, Haskell
can't adopt .NET's type system. It
wouldn't be Haskell anymore. So it just
was somehow not a good fit. So Don uh
then filled that gap by saying, "All
right, let's design a functional
language whose high-order bit is it's a
.NET language." All right. So now lots
of design decisions are made for you.
Yeah.
That's really good because then you
don't have to make them. Now let's try
to inject all the good stuff we can
about functional programming into that.
Yeah.
So in effect, there's you know, he's
filling a different kind of niche.
Haskell is playing the the um principled
laboratory in which a lot of ideas grow
that F# F# recently adopted an idea
called workflows which are just monads
with a friendlier name.
But they came straight from Haskell and
Don is careful to say that whenever he
describes them.
Nice of him to do so. But I so I think I
often see Haskell as a kind of
laboratory in which ideas can grow up.
But it is also a practical vehicle. Lots
of people use it for real applications.
GMT is is right up there. If you look at
the language shootout which is slightly
dubious
dubious mechanism. But it has it's a
sort of very crude performance
comparison. It's no longer the case that
functional languages lag performance
dramatically.
Is there any specific language that
Haskell derives from or took influence
well of course any all the functional
stuff before it but is there anything
specific?
Oh there were several several important
functional lazy functional languages
that arrived at the time we designed
Haskell.
So KRC was one the Kent Recursive
Calculator and SASL both of which were
designed by David Turner who is a very
important figure in these early 80s of
functional programming. His was his
papers on SK combinator reductions that
first got me excited about functional
programming in the first place. So his
languages SASL KRC and Miranda were very
important input. ML was an important
input
and a language called Lazy ML a variant
from Chalmers University.
And there were a couple of others but
those were probably the big inputs.
There's a paper called the history of
Haskell on my homepage actually. A
little while ago last year there was the
history of programming languages
conference.
Yeah. Ah you were there right?
So we wrote a yes I gave a talk about
the history of Haskell. So there's a
sort of 60 page epic paper describing
some of these early experiences of why
the language got designed who designed
it and why.
So so you can it's a it's a it's an easy
read actually and there'll be a video
sometime.
And we'll put a link to that into the
show notes. So last question before we
finish this up
if somebody wants to learn Haskell
Is there a good book?
Where do you get started? How do you get
started?
So the
place that I would definitely start if I
was learning Haskell would be to go to
haskell.org. There are various
tutorials, there are quite a few
tutorials there.
There are quite a few books. There's an
older book called The Craft of
Functional Programming by Simon Thompson
and The School of Expression by Paul
Hudak and a more recent one by Graham
Hutton called uh is it Functional
Programming in Haskell? There's a very
recent book that isn't quite out yet.
Which actually might I would think in
the end might be more suitable for your
audience, which is called uh Real World
Haskell. If you just type that into
Google, you'll get to it very quickly.
It's being authored at the moment.
Various various chapters are available.
There's and and you have the opportunity
if you look now to give the authors
feedback on their chapters. You can say
this part was completely opaque or why
don't you have a chapter about this? So
it's being developed in a rather
open-sourcey kind of way.
Um but the other thing is that I would
really get onto the Haskell Cafe mailing
list or the Haskell IRC channel. For
some reason, the Haskell community is a
very friendly one. So you can ask
extremely stupid questions and you'll
get extremely quick and friendly
replies. You will not get any you know
you idiot.
Okay, anything else we didn't cover?
Anything you know any words of wisdom
you want to leave with our listeners?
One reason that I came today and the
about the talk I gave was saying that I
think that whether or not you adopt
functional programming as being
the way of the future under that brand,
somehow or other this business of
controlling effects is going to be
important.
And if it's going to be important, then
it's a good idea for professional
programmers to have an idea of what
that's about. way to do that is to learn
a functional programming language. And
figure it out. So I'd encourage you to
just have a go. It's it's really good
fun.
It's you you definitely got to download
an interpreter and download GHCI so you
can run it.
You don't get it from reading a book. It
requires a little bit of brain rewiring
to learn a functional language. There's
no two ways about it. You just and you
just have to think oh I'm going to going
to spend a little bit of while rewiring
my brain. But it's the most exciting
thing since sliced bread and I do think
that this whole parallelism stuff is
going to be important and uh
and uh that's that's So, that's one of
my active research areas at the moment
is nested data parallelism. I want to
get data parallelism to work really well
in Haskell.
Mhm.
Uh doesn't tell me much. Don't don't
know.
The data parallelism is the way you're
going to harness lots of processors when
you got lots of data. Data parallelism
means do the same thing to every element
of an array.
Okay. Yeah.
But current instantiation When people
say data parallelism today, they mean
MPI and high-performance Fortran and C
and that and and indeed MapReduce,
Google's MapReduce. And it's always flat
data parallelism, which is good for
particular kinds of problems where you
want to do something to every element of
an aggregate, but the something is
sequential. Nested data parallelism, an
idea invented by a guy Carnegie Mellon,
or rather popularized by him, guy called
Guy Blelloch is his name.
Mhm.
Uh so, he showed how to take a program
where you do in data parallel, you do to
every element of an array, but the thing
that you do is itself a data parallel
algorithm, and that can do data parallel
algorithms at to any depth. So, you get
this recursive nested structure that's
much more widely applicable, applicable
to much wider class of problems, sparse
arrays, graph algorithms, um search
algorithms, lots of
computationally intensive,
data-intensive algorithms.
Yeah.
And what I'm doing at the moment is it
trying to take Guy's ideas and with
colleagues at uh in the University of
New South Wales, lift them into the 21st
century in the context of this already
rather mature language, Haskell, so that
we can get
nested data parallelism to work in the
context of that language. So, that's my
current excitement.
Okay, very good. Thank you very much for
being on the show.
Yeah, thanks for having me.
Thank you.
Thanks for listening to Software
Engineering Radio. If you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes, visit our website at
se-radio.net.
If you want to support us, you can
donate to the SE Radio team via the
website, or you can advertise for SE
Radio, for example, by clicking on the
Digg, Reddit, Delicious, and Slashdot
buttons.
To contact the team, please send email
to team@se-radio.net,
or if it's specific to an episode,
please use the comments facility on the
website so other people can read and
react to your comments.
This episode of Software Engineering
Radio, as well as all other episodes,
are licensed under Creative Commons
License. Please see the website for
details.
Thanks to Charlie Crow and the Podsafe
Music Network for the music used in this
show. The song is called Vegas Hard Rock
Shuffle.